A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Community and Resource Development, Acting Director, Office Files of Carl Anthony FA507
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Community and Resource Development, Acting Director, Office Files of Carl Anthony
1998-2006 (Bulk: 2001-2006)
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA507
3.2 Cubic Feet
The Asset Building and Community Development Program was established in October 1996 as part of a Foundation-wide program reorganization. The new program supported the work of a range of groups and individuals seeking to build the assets and capacities of poor communities through community-based activities, research, policy analysis, and advocacy. The Assets Program had three program units: Economic Development; Community and Resource Development (CRD); and Human Development and Reproductive Health. Carl Anthony joined the Ford Foundation as a Program Officer within the Assets Program’s CRD Unit in 2001. In 2003, he became Deputy Director of Community and Resource Development and in 2004, Acting Director. As Program Officer, Anthony directed the Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI), the Foundation’s grantmaking portfolio in equitable and sustainable community development. He also participated in making substantial cross-portfolio investments in Regional Equity Demonstrations (REDs, singular RED). The Office Files of Carl Anthony span in date from 1999 to 2006 and primarily document his work as Program Officer. The bulk of the collection consists of grantee files, primarily of SMCI and RED grant recipients. These files contain correspondence, project updates, conference materials, products of Ford-funded research, and background information about grantees and projects. The collection also contains files on trips, conferences and meetings Anthony attended in his capacity as Program Officer and Acting Director.
(8 Hollinger document boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment. Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Organizational History
The Asset Building and Community Development Program was established in October 1996 as part of a Foundation-wide program reorganization. The new program brought together four previously separate Foundation programs in Urban Poverty, Rural Poverty and Resources, Reproductive Health and Population, and Program Related Investments. It supported the work of a range of groups and individuals seeking to build the assets and capacities of poor communities through community-based activities, research, policy analysis, and advocacy. The Assets Program had three program units: Economic Development; Community and Resource Development; and Human Development and Reproductive Health. In 2009, the Asset Building and Community Development Program became the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program.
Arrangement
Arranged into 5 series.
Scope and Content Note
The Office Files of Carl Anthony span in date from 1999 to 2006 and primarily document his work as Program Officer managing the Community and Resource Development Unit portfolio on regional equity and smart growth. The bulk of the collection consists of grantee files, primarily of recipients of grants under the Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI) and the Regional Equity Demonstrations (REDs). The collection also contains files on trips, conferences and meetings he attended in his capacity as Program Officer and Acting Director at Ford.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Biographical Note
Born in Philadelphia, Carl Anthony received a PhD in Architecture and Urban Planning from Columbia University. Between 1989 and 2001, he served as founding Executive Director of Urban Habitat, one of the nation’s oldest environmental and economic justice organizations.
In 2001, he joined the Ford Foundation as a Program Officer within the Assets Program’s Community and Resource Development (CRD) Unit. As Program Officer, he directed the Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI), the Foundation’s grantmaking portfolio in equitable and sustainable community development. SMCI sought to alleviate concentrated poverty resulting from public policies and business practices that promoted economically segregated communities and ecologically unsustainable growth. It supported grantees engaged in a wide range of work, including research and discussions on urban sprawl and smart growth; leadership and capacity building; policy development; and strategic communication influencing more equitable regional resource allocation.
As a CRD Unit program officer, Mr. Anthony also participated in making substantial cross-portfolio investments in Regional Equity Demonstrations (REDs, singular RED). REDs were practical learning applications and demonstrations of the Foundation’s regional approach to community development and urban revitalization. Then CRD Unit Director Cynthia Miller originally initiated RED as a unit-wide initiative designed to foster substantial cross-portfolio investments focused on racial justice and social equity in the City of Camden, New Jersey and its surrounding communities. REDs were initiated at four other locations: Richmond, California; Baltimore, Maryland; Detroit, Michigan; and Atlanta, Georgia. In Camden, New Jersey, where the majority of grant funds were invested, the Foundation promoted its regional equity agenda through targeted investments in the areas of real estate development, employment opportunities, public sector capacity, and civic engagement. Mr. Anthony continued the RED initiative through his tenure as CRD Unit Deputy Director in 2003 and Acting Director in 2004. With the selection of Suzanne Siskel as CRD Unit Director in 2006, RED came under the management of the single grant portfolio, SMCI.
In 2006, Mr. Anthony left the Foundation to become a Visiting Scholar and Ford Foundation Senior Fellow in the Department of Geography at the University of California Berkeley.
Conditions Governing Access note
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Date spans of this collection range from 1998-2006. As such, much of the material is closed to scholarly access until the applicable records are more than ten years old. Material will be open for research, as records reach the ten year threshold, 2016-2017.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Ford Foundation
- Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI) Files, 1998-2006; I (Box not specified)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Date spans of this series range from 1998-2006. As such, much of the material is closed to scholarly access until the applicable records are more than ten years old. Material will be open for research as records reach the ten year threshold, 2016-2017.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of subject files documenting the work of Sustainable Metropolitan Communities Initiative (SMCI) grantees. Files are arranged alphabetically by name of grantee or project and contain correspondence, conference materials, products of Ford-funded research, and background information about grantees and projects. The bulk of correspondence pertains to project updates and conference information grantees sent to Mr. Anthony. Files on conferences held by grantees, grantmaking partners or the Ford Foundation that Mr. Anthony kept with his SMCI files are included in this series. Additional conference files can be found in Series IV: Trips, Conferences and Meetings.
  - African American Forum on Race and Regionalism -- Memoranda Re: Meeting, Conference Call Agenda, Feb 17, 2004-Mar 17, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    File is closed to scholarly research.
    Date Restricted Material -- Contains records less than 10 years old -- Restricted records are Open to scholarly research in 2016.
  - African American Forum on Race and Regionalism -- Papers on Race and Regional Equity, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - African American Forum on Race and Regionalism -- Reception and Workshop at the NAACP National Convention, Philadelphia, PA, Jul 10-15, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Atlanta Neighborhood Development Partnership (ANDP) -- Correspondence, Published Report on Mixed Income and Mixed Use Communities, Apr 8, 2002-Jul 19, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bay Area Council -- Memoranda Re: Background for Conference Call, Report on Bay Area Family of Funds, Jan 12, 2003-Jun 29, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Center for Community Change -- Correspondence, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Collins Center for Public Policy -- Correspondence Re: Building a Region of Strong Neighborhoods in South Florida, Mar 6, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Commonweal -- "Conversations with Advocates of Fair Growth" (interviews by Steve Lerner) (1 of 2), Oct 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Commonweal -- "Conversations with Advocates of Fair Growth" (interviews by Steve Lerner) (2 of 2), Oct 2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Commonweal -- "Smart Growth/Fair Growth: Building Mixed-Income Communities" (report by Steve Lerner) (1 of 2), 2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Commonweal -- "Smart Growth/Fair Growth: Building Mixed-Income Communities" (report by Steve Lerner) (2 of 2), 2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Earth House -- Information Kits on SMCI, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Earth House -- Internal Communications Audit Summary Report, Interview Notes, Dec 2002-May 2003 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Earth House -- Strategic Communications for SMCI, 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Date Restricted Material -- Contains records less than 10 years old -- Restricted records are Open to scholarly research in 2017.
  - Earth House -- Strategic Communications Meeting Notes, Charts, Planning Report, Email, Dec 2002-May 2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Earth House -- Strategic Communications Plan (separated), Sep 2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Earth House -- Strategic Communications Work Plans and Reports, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Environmental Justice Resource Center -- Correspondence, Report on Strategies for Achieving Environmental, Racial and Economic Justice, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ferris, Deeohn -- SMCI Project on African American Perspectives on Regionalism, Regional Equity and Smart Growth, 1998-2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gamaliel Foundation -- National Leadership Assembly "Eyes on the Prize: Coalitions to Win Metro Equity" -- Agenda, Conference Book, Dec 5-7, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - George Washington University Center on Sustainable Growth -- Report and Research on Sustainable Metropolitan Communities, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Good Jobs First -- Correspondence, Clippings Re: Smart Growth and Unions, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Good Jobs First -- Monograph and Summary Report of Interviews of Labor Union Leaders on Smart Growth, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Greater Baltimore Urban League -- Correspondence Re: Transportation Project, Comprehensive Social Equity Study Update, etc., Jun 3, 2002-Nov 3, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Harvard University Civil Rights Project -- Round Table on Transportation Equity -- Agenda, Discussion Questions, Participant List, Concept Paper, Invitation, Jun 9, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Institute on Race and Poverty -- Conference on Race and Regionalism, Minneapolis, MN -- Correspondence, Conference Book, Summary, May 6-7, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Institute on Race and Poverty -- Correspondence, Papers on Race, Regional Equity and Urban Sprawl, 1998-2003 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - InterValley Project (IVP) -- Correspondence, Meeting Agenda, Background on Issue Campaigns and Brownfield Organizing, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Metro Organization for Racial and Economic Equity -- Summit on Racism and Metropolitan Dynamics: Organizing for Statewide Solutions -- Agenda, Background, Jun 21, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - National Economic Development and Law Center (NEDLC) -- Concept Paper on Community Capital Investment Initiative (CCII), May 12, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - National Neighborhood Coalition (NNC) -- Correspondence, Background on NNC, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - National Vacant Properties Campaign -- Research and Policy Forum to Identify Campaign Priorities Creating Opportunity from Abandonment, Washington, DC, Jul 28-29, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - PolicyLink -- Advancing Regional Equity: Second Annual Summit on Equitable Development, Social Justice and Smart Growth, Philadelphia, PA, May 23-25, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - PolicyLink and Funders' Network for Smart Growth and Livable Communities -- Promoting Regional Equity: A National Summit on Equitable Development, Social Justice and Smart Growth, Los Angeles, CA, Nov 17-19, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Redefining Progress -- Correspondence, Background on Common Assets Program, Sustainability Indicators Program, etc., Oct 2001-Dec 2003 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Regional Plan Association (RPA) -- 14th Annual Regional Assembly, New York, NY -- Reports, Lists of Speakers, Participants and Workshops, Apr 16, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Regional Plan Association (RPA) -- Civic Alliance to Rebuild Downtown New York -- Meeting Notes, Resolutions, Prospectus Outline, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Rochester (City of) -- Rochester Conversation on Mid-Size Cities -- Correspondence, Agenda, Published Summary, Nov 12-13, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Surface Transportation Policy Project -- Correspondence, Interim Report, Draft Policy Statement, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Torrice Productions -- Correspondence Re: Funding Production of Documentary "The New Metropolis", Oct-Nov 2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Transportation and Land Use Coalition (TALC) -- Correspondence, Narrative on Great Communities Initiative, Oct 2002-Jun 2006 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Some of the records in this file are restricted because they are less than 10 years old. The restricted items have been segregated and are inaccessible. The file is open to research, and physical removal of the segregated material is not necessary.
    Date Restricted Material -- Contains records less than 10 years old -- Restricted records are Open to scholarly research in 2016 and 2017.
  - Working Partnerships USA -- Correspondence from Amy B. Dean Re: Project Support, Move to Chicago, etc., May 2003 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Regional Equity Demonstration (RED) Files, 1999-2006; II (Box not specified)
  This series consists of files documenting the Ford Foundation Community and Resource Development (CRD) Unit’s Regional Equity Demonstrations (REDs). Although there are a few files on other RED project locations, files on the RED project in Camden, New Jersey constitute the bulk of the series. Camden RED files consist of correspondence, meeting materials, proposals, and background information on Camden, grantees and projects. Several files document various RED staff meetings as well as the Foundation’s partnership and collaboration with The Reinvestment Fund (TRF), the Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) and the Annie E. Casey Foundation.
  In addition, there are three files pertaining to the work of consultant David Rusk. Mr. Rusk prepared activity reports, recommendations, and papers in his role as advisor to the CRD Unit in national strategies for regional reform and as a resource for Ford grantees in Atlanta, Baltimore, Detroit, Philadelphia and Camden.
  - Annie E. Casey Foundation -- Consultative Session on Responsible Relocation, Mar 16-17, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Annie E. Casey Foundation and the Camden Development Collaborative -- Correspondence, Camden Funders Report, Background, 2000-2006 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Camden Churches Organized for the People, Inc. (CCOP) -- Correspondence, Background, Presentation Given During Site Visit, 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Camden Redevelopment Agency Reorganization Proposal, [2002] (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Concordia LLC -- Proposal, Report, Appendix of Meeting Summaries and Interviews, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Council of New Jersey Grantmakers -- Correspondence, Meeting and Convening Materials on Regional Equity Project in Southern Jersey, Proposal, 2002-2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Energy Programs Consortium -- Weatherization, Rehab and Asset Preservation (WRAP) Partnership -- Background, Jan 15, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hatcher Group -- Correspondence, Summary Recommendations for Communicating Ford Foundation Work in Camden, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Invest in Camden Day Conference, Camden, NJ -- Agenda, Brochures on Camden Organizations and Development Projects, Jan 23, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports Prepared for Meetings with Ford Foundation, 2002-2005 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - New Jersey Institute for Social Justice -- Meeting on Regional Equity, Civil Rights and the Low-Income Housing Tax Credit Program -- Correspondence, Agenda, Background Paper, May 6, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New Jersey Regional Coalition (NJRC) -- Briefing on New Jersey Political Environment and Legislation, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - PolicyLink -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Regional Equity/Equitable Development Strategy, Apr 29, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Regional and Neighborhood Equity Project (RNEP) Meeting (7/28-29/2005) -- Agenda, Correspondence, Background, Jun-Jul 2005 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - RED -- Background and Descriptions of the Community and Resource Development (CRD) Unit and RED, 2003-2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - RED -- Ford Foundation Community and Resource Development (CRD) Unit Site Visit to Camden, Nov 21, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - RED -- Report to the Ford Foundation on the Camden Environmental Justice Scan, Jan 16, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - RED -- Research and Reports on Camden, NJ, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - RED Meetings -- Agendas, Memoranda, Notes, Background, 2002-2004 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - RED Program Officer Meeting -- Summary, RED FAP Overview, Apr 20-May 11, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - RED Staff Planning Meetings and Retreat -- Agenda, Strategic Plan, Retreat Notes, Sep 2004-May 2005 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - RED Stakeholders Meetings (9/30/2003 and 11/20/2003) -- Meeting Summary, Invitation, Agenda (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Reinventing America's Older Communities Conference, Philadelphia, PA -- Agenda, Draft Problem Statement Re: Small Weak Market Cities, Jan 14-16, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Reinvestment Fund (TRF) -- Correspondence, Paper, Background on Project Based Regionalism in Camden, NJ, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Richmond Initiative -- Project Overview, Analysis of Proposed Just Cause/Fair Rent Ordinance for Richmond by Urban Habitat, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Rusk, David -- Consultant Activity Reports, Speeches, 1999-2004 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Rusk, David -- Draft Paper on Measuring Regional Equity, Summary of Paper, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Rusk, David -- The People's Summit for Regional Equity -- Program, Participant List, Presentation, Jun 27, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - The Trust for Public Land -- Advisory Council Meeting Minutes, Background on Camden, NJ, Jan 9-10, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - University of California Santa Cruz Center for Justice, Tolerance & Community (CJTC) -- Conversation on Regional Equity (CORE) Meeting -- Agenda, Minutes, Summary, Background, Participant Bios, Feb 24-25, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - University of California Santa Cruz Center for Justice, Tolerance & Community (CJTC) -- Conversation on Regional Equity (CORE) Meeting -- Agenda, Report, Background, Participant Bios, Oct 3-5, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - University of California Santa Cruz Center for Justice, Tolerance & Community (CJTC) - Conversation on Regional Equity (CORE) Meeting -- Agenda, Report, Comments, Participants List, Jan 17-18, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Urban Habitat -- Overview of Strategic Communication Needs and Transcript of Interview Between Carl Anthony, Juliet Ellis and Angela Glover-Blackwell, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Grant-Related Files, 2001-2005; III (Box not specified)
  Date spans of this series range from 2001-2005. As such, much of the material is closed to scholarly access until the applicable records are more than ten years old. Material will be open for research as records reach the ten year threshold, 2016.
  This series consists of files relating to grants Mr. Anthony managed within his program area of regional equity and smart growth. Mr. Anthony kept these files as part of his General Files. They are maintained as a separate series because it is unclear whether these grants were issued as part of the SMCI or RED initiatives. Files contain correspondence and memoranda along with attached proposals, meeting notes, agenda and background materials regarding proposed or then-ongoing grant activity. One highlight is a file that documents Mr. Anthony’s involvement in the creation of the Funder’s Network, a resource for foundations, nonprofit organizations and other partners working to address problems resulting from suburban sprawl and urban disinvestment.
  - The Funders' Network -- IRS Agreement, Papers on Smart Growth Issues, Meeting Notes, 2001-2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Living Cities: The National Community Development Initiative -- Agenda, Email Correspondence, Discussion Paper on Shaping Public Policy (1 of 2), 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    File is closed to scholarly research. Date Restricted Material -- Contains records less than 10 years old -- Restricted records are Open to scholarly research in 2016.
  - Living Cities -- Meeting Book with Agenda, Memoranda, Background (2 of 2), 2005 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Public Sector Mapping Project -- Memoranda, Papers on Workforce Development Perspective, Homeland Security, etc., 2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Regional Equity -- Notes, Agenda, PowerPoint, Program Officer Memorandum, Apr-Jun 2003 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Selecting and Working with Public Relations Firms: A Guide for Grantmakers", May 2003 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sexual and Reproductive Health -- Memoranda, Background, Human Rights Meeting Minutes and Materials, 2002-2004 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Study on Urbanization, Environment and Development in Africa -- Background Papers, 2005-2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Trips, Conferences and Meetings, 2001-2005; IV (Box not specified)